Jean Liberte Papers
Jean Liberte Papers
1924-1971
Liberte, Jean, 1896-1965.
4.0 linear ft.
Papers of the Italian-American painter including correspondence, reproductions of his art, clippings, photographs and other memorabilia
149133
Biographical History
Jean Liberté (1896-1965) was an Italian-American artist. Born in Italy, Liberté emigrated to the United States in 1900 and became a citizen in 1932. He received his art education at Cooper Union and studied under Arthur Crisp, David Karfunkle, and Kenneth Hayes Miller at the Art Students League in New York City. Liberté also attended the National Academy of Design and the Beaux-Arts Institute for a short time. From 1946 until his death, Liberté taught painting at the Art Students League and casein painting at the North Shore (New York) Community Center Art School; he was also visiting lecturer for the Great Neck (New York) Art Association, Scarsdale Art Center, and the Roslyn (New York) Art Center.
Liberté exhibited in many one-man shows and shows with others throughout the world, and his work is represented in the permanent collections of many important galleries. He received numerous awards as a recognized authority on the technical aspects of casein painting and commendations for his experiments in gouache.
Liberté was married to the former Ruth Rita Kagan, a fellow artist. They had no children.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jean Liberté Papers are divided into correspondence-subject files, artwork reproductions, and memorabilia. The bulk of the material in the latter two categories is not dated.
Correspondence-subject files covers 1924-1971, with emphasis on 1933-1935, and includes both incoming and outgoing letters. Significant correspondents include artists with whom he collaborated at Yaddo and at the Art Students League and his wife, artist Ruth Rita Kagan (letters dated from 1924 to 1943).
Material in Artwork reproductions is entirely undated, and includes photographs of Liberté's paintings plus two reproductions of artwork by Ruth Rita Kagan Liberté.
Memorabilia includes awards, clippings, photographs (including three studies of Martha Graham by Soichi Sunami), printed material and a poster for an exhibit of the sculpture of Samuel Adler.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically by name or subject. Artwork reproductions are arranged alphabetically by title or description with works by Jean Liberte first and Ruth Kagan Liberte second. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Liberte, Jean, 1896-1965.; Liberte, Ruth Kagan.; Becker, Maurice, 1889-1975.; Benno, Benjamin, 1901-1980.; DeMartini, Joseph, 1896-1984.; Edie, Stuart, 1908-1974.; Foy, Hans.; Hios, Theo, 1908-1999.; Smith, Jacob Getlar, 1898-1958.; Sunami, Soichi, 1885-1971.; Art Students League (New York, N.Y.); Butler Institute of American Art.; Columbia University.; National Academy of Design (U.S.); Treasury Relief Art Project.; Yaddo (Artists' colony); Art, American.; Art -- Political Aspects -- United States.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Art Schools -- United States.; Italian Americans.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Awards.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Invitations.; Photographs.; Programs (documents); Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. R. Liberte, 1970.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Advancing American Art Exhibition, 1947 (Box 1)
  - The American Historical Company, Inc., 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Art Students League, New York, 1953; 1964-1970 (Box 1)
  - Artists Equity Association, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Audubon Artists, New York, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Becker, Maurice and Dorothy Baldwin, 1934; 1949 (Box 1)
  - Benno, Benjamin, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Berkshire Art Center, Canaan, New York, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Community School, 1952 (Box 1)
  - The Butler Institute of American Art, Youngstown, Ohio, 1954; 1959,; 1968-1973 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Comen, Suetelle, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Committee of Artists' Societies, 1964 (Box 1)
  - DeVitis, Themis, 1964 (Box 1)
  - DeMartini, Joseph, 1935; 1965,; undated (Box 1)
  - Dirk, Nathaniel, 1934; 1961 (Box 1)
  - Edie, Stuart, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Eighth Street Gallery, New York, undated (Box 1)
  - Fiorello, Dante, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Foy, Hans, undated (Box 1)
  - The Gallery of Modern Art, New York, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Hios, Theo, undated (Box 1)
  - Hondius, Gerrit, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Institute of International Education, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - The Jean Liberte Memorial Scholarship, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Karfunkle, David, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Kessler, Paul, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Liberte, Ruth Kagan, 1924; 1933; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Liberte, Ruth Kagan, 1934; 1935-1938,; 1940-1943,; undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Liberte, Salvatore C., 1945 (Box 2)
  - MacLane, M. Jean, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Metcalf, Evelyn, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1941 (Box 2)
  - The Museum of Modern Art, New York, 1966 (Box 2)
  - National Academy of Design, 1950 (Box 2)
  - National Association of Women Artists, Inc., 1953 (Box 2)
  - Newark School of Fine and Industrial Art, Newark, New Jersey, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Pavillion of Fine Arts New York Worlds Fair, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Pollard, Paul, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Schaeffer, H. Bela, undated (Box 2)
  - Sheffield, Emily, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - Sheffield, Marion, 1933-1934; 1967 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Jacob Getlar, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Smithsonian Institution National Gallery of Fine Arts, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Snow, Edith A., 1934 (Box 2)
  - Treasury Relief Art Project, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Waldemar Medical Research Foundation, Inc., 1958 (Box 2)
  - Westchester Arts and Crafts Guild, White Plains, New York, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Wilder Charlotte, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Yaddo, 1932-1934 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1932-1958; 1965-1971,; undated (Box 2)
- Artwork reproductions
  - Liberté, L. Jean
    - Early Painting untitled (Box 3)
    - "Fog at Grand Manan" (Box 3)
    - A group of paintings at the Babcock Gallery, New York (Oversize 1)
    - "Mother and Two Children" (Box 3)
    - "Mother of Spain" (Box 3)
    - "New England Wharf" (Box 3)
    - "New York City" (Box 3)
    - Nudes untitled (Box 3)
    - "Part of Gloucester" (Box 3)
    - "Portrait of a Woman (Ruth)" (Box 3)
    - "Road in Monhegan" (Box 3)
    - "The Sea Coast of Maine" (Box 3)
    - "Serenity" (Box 3)
    - Sketch study untitled (Box 3)
    - "Yaddo Road" (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous untitled (Box 3)
  - Liberté, Ruth Rita Kagan
    - "Clown at Circus" (Box 3)
    - "Jamaica" (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Artwork reproductions by others (Oversize 1)
  - Awards and certificates (Oversize 1)
  - Clippings about Liberte and his work (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Art Students League (Box 3)
    - Family and friends (Box 3)
    - Jean and Ruth Liberte (Box 3)
    - Photographs of Martha Graham by Soichi Sunami (Box 3)
    - Reference images (Box 3)
    - Studio and exhibitions (Oversize 1)
  - Printed material
    - Exhibitions featuring works by Jean Liberte and Ruth Kagan Liberte (Box 3)
    - Drawings by American Artists by Norman Kent, 1947 (Oversize 1)
    - Modern American Painting by Peyton Roswell, Jr., 1939 (Oversize 1)
    - Miscelaneous (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Cemetery bill and cremation certificate (Box 3)
    - Poster Frank Rehn Gallery, 1971 (Oversize 2)
    - General (Box 3)